# Heath O'Brien, PhD Bioinformatician

May 2022

hobrien.github.io

heath.obrien@gmail.com

heath\_obrien

hobrien

Publications

**in** genome-informatics

## About me ———

I have 20 years of experience analyzing genetic data, both in academia and the private sector. I've worked on functional genomics, high-throughput sequencing and genotyping data from plants, fungi, bacteria and humans. I enjoy working on interdisciplinary projects and leading teams with diverse skill sets. I also have strong communication skills, having co-authored over 25 publications and presented my research at conferences in 7 countries.

# Skills —

Functional genomics

Quantitative genetics

Microbiology

Data visualisation

Scientific communication

Project management

R

Python

BASH

**AWS** 

SQL

#### **Work History**

2020-2022 Bioinformatician

Theolytics

- Managing pipelines and compute architecture for genomic analyses of oncolytic viruses
- Advising on research strategy and on the design and analysis of experiments
- Managing partnerships with other companies and academic scientists

2018-2020 Lead Bioinformatician

Living DNA

- Leading a team of 6 bioinformaticians and data scientists developing methods to derive ancestry and health insights from genotyping data
- Working to secure external funding to develop novel genomic prediction approaches
- Collaboration with the engineering team to deploy processing pipelines at scale and to improve all steps of sample processing and data delivery

2016-2018 Research Associate

Cardiff, UK

Oxford UK

Frome, UK

MRC Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics

- Differential gene expression and eQTL analyses on human brain samples
- Integration of functional genomic and large-scale population genetic datasets for schizophrenia and other neurophychiatric disorders
- Organization of training seminars on data science (Rstudio, MySQL), version control (Git), and pipeline development (Snakemake, Bash)
- Deployment of results on the web using R-Shiny

2013-2016 Bioinformatician

Bristol, UK

University of Bristol

- Comparative transcriptomics to determine the genetic basis of cell wall patterning responsible for colour-production in plant leaves
- Acting group leader during nine-month family leave cover (overseeing a team of three staff and two students, managing procurement)

2008-2013 Postdoctoral Fellow

Toronto, ON, Canada

University of Toronto

- Comparative analyses of bacterial genomes
- Cloning of virulence factors and characterization using in-planta infection assays

2006-2008 Lab Administrator

Durham, NC, USA

**Duke University** 

- Oversight of Microbiology teaching labs
- Managed one lab technician and eight teaching assistants

#### Education

2000-2006 PhD, Molecular systematics of cyanobacteria

Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

1994-1999 Bachelors degree, Plant Science University of Alberta

Edmonton, AB, Canada

## Training

Advanced Python for Biologists, PR Statistics, February, 2017. Advancing in R, PR Statistics, April, 2015.

Genetic Data Analysis, Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics, June, 2003.

#### References

Available on request.